Kaede
Two
Years
Ago
Two
Years
Ago
Kaede
そろそろ:slowly/quietly|soon, 起きる[おきる]:to get up|to wake up|to occur (usu. of unfavourable incidents)
⦅咲太:花楓 そろそろ起きろ｡
Time to wake up, Kaede.
朝ごはん[あさごはん]:breakfast
朝ごはんができるぞ｡
Breakfast's almost ready.
(花楓)だ 誰ですか!?
は？
Wh-Who are you?!
Huh?
えっ ここ どこですか？
私… え なんですか？ これ…｡
Wh-Where am I?
I... Who...
What's going on?
花楓…｡
Kaede?
症状[しょうじょう]:symptoms/condition
花楓さんの症状は
Kaede-san's symptoms indicate
Episode 12: Living the Continuation of an Endless Dream
解離[かいり]:dissociation, 性[さが, なりくせ]:one's nature/one's destiny|custom, 性[せい]:nature (of a person)|sex|gender|, 障害[しょうがい, しょうげ]:obstacle/impediment|handicap, 一種[いっしゅ, ひとくさ]:species/kind/variety
解離性障害の一種だと思われます｡
a form of dissociative disorder.
Dissociative... disorder?
解離[かいり]:dissociation, 性[さが, なりくせ]:one's nature/one's destiny|custom, 性[せい]:nature (of a person)|sex|gender|, 障害[しょうがい, しょうげ]:obstacle/impediment|handicap
解離性… 障害？
感覚[かんかく]:sense/sensation/feeling, 意識[いしき]:consciousness|awareness|mano-vijnana (mental consciousness, cognizer of sensory information)
自分が自分であるという感覚や
意識が
It's an illness where one loses
their identity—their sense of self.
失う[うしなう]:to lose/to part with, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.), 病気[びょうき]:illness/disease/sickness
失われてしまう病気です｡
今回[こんかい]:now/this time/lately, ケース:case (e.g. receptacle, condition, event, legal action, letter style, etc.)
今回の花楓さんのｹｰｽのように
Just like in Kaede-san's case,
記憶[きおく]:memory/recollection|storage, 欠落[けつらく]:missing/lacking, 喪失[そうしつ]:loss/forfeit, かたち:form/shape|visage
記憶の欠落や
喪失といったかたちで
there are many patients whose symptoms
include missing or lost memories.
症状[しょうじょう]:symptoms/condition, 現れる[あらわれる]:to appear/to come in sight|to be expressed (e.g. emotions), 患者[かんじゃ]:(a) patient
症状が現れる患者さんもいます｡
今の花楓さんには 今日までの
Right now, she has no memories of the life
she lived with you, her family.
両親[りょうしん, ふたおや]:parents/both parents, お兄さん[おにいさん]:older brother/elder brother|(vocative) young man, 過ごす[すごす]:to pass (time)|to overdo (esp. of one's alcohol consumption)|to take care of||, 記憶[きおく]:memory/recollection|storage
ご両親や お兄さんと過ごした
記憶がありません｡
But why?
どうして そんな…｡
Possible causes include extreme stress
and mental trauma.
原因[げんいん]:cause/origin/source, 極度[きょくど]:maximum/extreme/utmost, ストレス:stress, 心的外傷[しんてきがいしょう]:psychic trauma/psychological trauma, 考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||
原因としては 極度のｽﾄﾚｽや
心的外傷が考えられます⦆
Possible causes include extreme stress
and mental trauma.
かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.), たしか:sure/certain|reliable, コミュニティー:community
(麻衣)かえでちゃん
たしか SNSのｺﾐｭﾆﾃｨｰに
Kaede-chan developed Puberty Syndrome
after being bashed on a message board, right?
悪口[あっこう, わるくち]:abuse/insult/slander, 書く[かく]:to write/to compose|to draw, 原因[げんいん]:cause/origin/source, 思春期[ししゅんき]:puberty, 症候群[しょうこうぐん]:syndrome
悪口を書かれたのが原因で
思春期症候群になったのよね｡
苦しむ[くるしむ]:to suffer/to groan/to be worried
そうです｡ それで
かえでは苦しんで
Right.
She suffered from bullying,
drop dead, kaede
つらい:painful/bitter|tough, 押し潰す[おしつぶす]:to squash/to crush/to flatten, 状態[じょうたい]:current status/condition/situation
つらくて つらくて
押し潰されそうな状態から
and in order to escape her painful
and oppressive situation,
抜け出す[ぬけだす]:to slip out/to sneak away|to break (out of a loop), 記憶[きおく]:memory/recollection|storage, 一部[いちぶ]:one part/one portion|one copy (e.g. of a document), 自ら[おのずから]:naturally/as a matter of course, 自ら[みずから]:oneself|for one's self/personally, 切り離す[きりはなす]:to detach/to decapitate/to cut loose
抜け出すために 記憶の一部を
自ら切り離したんです｡
she cut off a part of her memories herself.
壊れる[こわれる]:to be broken/to break|to fall through, 守る[まもる]:to protect/to guard|to keep (i.e. a promise)
壊れそうになった自分を
守るために｡
It was all she could do to prevent herself from breaking down.
解離[かいり]:dissociation
それが解離…｡
And that's how she dissociated?
After she lost her memories,
I had no idea how to interact with her at first.
記憶[きおく]:memory/recollection|storage, なくす:to lose something|to get rid of, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.), かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.), 接する[せっする]:to touch|to receive (e.g. visitor)|to receive (news)||
記憶をなくしてしまったかえでに
どう接したらいいのか…｡
最初[さいしょ]:beginning/outset/first, とまどう:to be bewildered/to be perplexed, ばかり:only/merely|approximately
最初は とまどってばかりでした｡
本[もと]:origin|base|cause||, 本[ほん]:book|this|main||, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
⦅花楓 本持ってきたぞ｡
Kaede, I brought you a book.
新刊[しんかん]:new book/new publication, 楽しみにする[たのしみにする]:to look forward to something
新刊が出るのを
楽しみにしてたやつ｡
The new volume you were so excited about.
ありがとう:Thank you/Thanks, ござる:to be
ほら｡
ありがとうございます｡
Here.
The Prince
and the
Cranky Witch
The Prince
and the
Cranky Witch
The Prince
and the
Cranky Witch
The Prince
and the
Cranky Witch
Th-Thank you.
The Prince
and the
Cranky Witch
The Prince
and the
Cranky Witch
The Prince
and the
Cranky Witch
The Prince
and the
Cranky Witch
The Prince
and the
Cranky Witch
The Prince
and the
Cranky Witch
The Prince
and the
Cranky Witch
The Prince
and the
Cranky Witch
The Prince
and the
Cranky Witch
The Prince
and the
Cranky Witch
The Prince
and the
Cranky Witch
えっと:let me see/well/errr ..., 本[もと]:origin|base|cause||, 本[ほん]:book|this|main||, 好き[すき]:liking/fondness/love, 好き[ずき]:-phil/-phile|being attractive (to)
えっと… 花楓さんは
この本が好きなんですか？⦆
Er... Did Kaede-san like this series?
The way she spoke was different.
話す[はなす]:to talk|to tell|to speak (a language), 方[かた]:direction|person|method of||, 方[ほう]:direction|side (of an argument, etc.)|type||, 箸[はし]:chopsticks, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
話し方が違う
箸を持つ手が違う｡
Her dominant hand was different.
ご飯[ごはん]:cooked rice|meal, おかず:side dish/okazu|food for thought (esp. in the context of conversation, or material for assisting arousal during masturbation), 食べる[たべる]:to eat|to live on (e.g. a salary)/to live off, 順番[じゅんばん]:turn (in line)/order of things/sequential order
ご飯とおかずの食べる順番が違う｡
The order she ate her food in was different.
パジャマ:pajamas/pyjamas, ボタン:button, ボタン:tree peony (Paeonia suffruticosa)/moutan, とめる:to stop/to turn off|to park, とめる:to give shelter to/to lodge/to put up
ﾊﾟｼﾞｬﾏのﾎﾞﾀﾝを上からとめる｡
She now buttoned her pajamas from the top.
She way she walked was different.
歩く[あるく]:to walk, 方[かた]:direction|person|method of||, 方[ほう]:direction|side (of an argument, etc.)|type||
歩き方が違う 花楓とは違う…｡
She was not the Kaede I knew.
Anything and everything about her had changed.
違う 違う…
何もかもが違う…｡
I'm back.
ただいま:Here I am/I'm home!|presently, おかえりなさい:welcome home
⦅ただいま｡
おかえりなさい｡
Welcome home.
Thanks.
Mom! Kaede's...
母さん[かあさん, かかさん]:mother|wife (used when speaking to or about one's own wife), かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.), 体[からだ]:body|torso|build||, 体[たい]:body|shape|substance||
母さん かえでが！
また花楓の体にｱｻﾞが！
She's got another bruise!
ああ そう｡
Oh, I see.
大丈夫よ 花楓｡
It's all right, Kaede.
大丈夫だからね⦆
Don't worry about a thing.
母さん[かあさん, かかさん]:mother|wife (used when speaking to or about one's own wife), 身[み]:body|oneself|one's place|, 身[むくろ]:(dead) body/corpse, 起きる[おきる]:to get up|to wake up|to occur (usu. of unfavourable incidents)
母さんは
花楓の身に起きたことを
Mom couldn't take what had happened to Kaede
and developed a mental illness.
It's all right. It's all right, Kaede.
受け止める[うけとめる]:to catch/to stop the blow|to react to, ことができる:can (do)/to be able to (do)/can be done
受け止めることができず
病気になる[びょうきになる]:to fall ill/to be taken ill, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
心の病気になってしまった｡
And then, I...
そして 僕も…｡
うっ…⦆
運ぶ[はこぶ]:to carry|to come|to wield (a tool, etc.)|, 病院[びょういん]:hospital, 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc., 信ずる[しんずる]:to believe/to believe in/to place trust in, もらえる:to be able to receive/to be able to take|could you (give me)
運ばれた病院でも 僕の話は
誰にも信じてもらえなかった｡
I was taken to a hospital,
and nobody there believed me.
いくら:how much?/how many?|even, 説明[せつめい]:explanation/exposition, 思い込み[おもいこみ]:wrong impression/subjective impression/assumption, 問題[もんだい]:question (e.g. on a test)|problem (e.g. societal, political)|question (i.e. doubt)||
いくら説明しても
ただの思い込み 心の問題
I tried and tried to explain,
but they only saw it as a delusion,
a mental issue,
自傷[じしょう]:self-mutilation/self-injury, 行為[こうい]:act/deed/conduct, 見てくれ[みてくれ]:appearance/outward show
自傷行為としか見てくれない…｡
and a form of self-harm.
僕は何もできなかった｡
I was powerless.
花楓に何もしてやれなかった｡
I couldn't do a thing for Kaede.
嫌[いや, や]:disagreeable/detestable/unpleasant, 病院[びょういん]:hospital, 抜け出す[ぬけだす]:to slip out/to sneak away|to break (out of a loop)
何もかも嫌になった僕は
あるとき病院を抜け出しました｡
Sick and tired of it all,
I snuck out of the hospital one day.
And that was when I met her.
出会う[であう]:to meet (by chance)|to meet (e.g. of rivers, highways, etc.)|to emerge and engage (an enemy)
そこで 彼女に出会ったんです｡
⦅翔子:知ってますか？
Did you know?
高い[たかい]:high/tall|expensive, 見える[みえる]:to be seen|to look|to come, 見える[まみえる]:to have an audience|to face (an enemy)|to serve (esp. as one's wife), 水平[すいへい]:level/horizontality, 線[せん]:line|line (e.g. telephone line)|ray (e.g. X-ray)||, 距離[きょり]:distance/range
人の目の高さから見える
水平線までの距離は
The distance from your eye level to the horizon
約[やく]:approximately|promise|shortening|
約４kmなんですよ⦆
is around four kilometers.
話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc., 黙る[だまる]:to be silent, 全部[ぜんぶ]:all/entire/whole, 信ずる[しんずる]:to believe/to believe in/to place trust in
翔子さんは 僕の話を黙って聞いて
全部信じてくれたんです｡
Shouko-san heard me out and believed it all.
たびたび:often/again and again/over and over again, 病院[びょういん]:hospital, 抜け出す[ぬけだす]:to slip out/to sneak away|to break (out of a loop)
それから 僕は たびたび病院を
抜け出すようになりました｡
After that, I started sneaking out frequently.
海[うみ, み]:sea/ocean/waters, さんがい:the three realms of existence|the whole universe (of a billion worlds) that Buddha enlightened, さんがい:third floor
七里ヶ浜の海には
いつも翔子さんがいた｡
If I went to Shichirigahama Beach,
I'd always find Shouko-san there.
妹[いもうと]:younger sister, 妹[いも]:darling (only of a woman)|one's sister|friend, 考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||
⦅また妹さんのこと
考えてたんですか？
Were you thinking about your sister again?
No, I was thinking about you.
考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||
翔子さんのことを
考えてました｡
なるほど:I see/That's right!/Indeed, エッチ:H/h
なるほど ｴｯﾁなことですね｡
違いますよ｡
Ah, I get it. You were having dirty thoughts?
No. I was wondering why you believe me.
信ずる[しんずる]:to believe/to believe in/to place trust in
どうして 翔子さんは
信じてくれるのかと思って｡
傷[きず, キズ]:wound|chip|flaw||
ん？
花楓の傷とか ｱｻﾞとか
About Kaede's cuts and bruises,
and about Puberty Syndrome.
思春期[ししゅんき]:puberty, 症候群[しょうこうぐん]:syndrome, いくら:how much?/how many?|even, 話す[はなす]:to talk|to tell|to speak (a language)
思春期症候群のこととか
いくら話しても
Nobody else cares what I have to say.
まとも:the front|honesty/uprightness
誰も まともに聞いてくれない｡
Nobody else even tries to believe
the things I've seen.
信ずる[しんずる]:to believe/to believe in/to place trust in
誰も僕の見たことを
信じようとしてくれない｡
見える[みえる]:to be seen|to look|to come, 見える[まみえる]:to have an audience|to face (an enemy)|to serve (esp. as one's wife), 世界[せかい]:the world|sphere|renowned|, 数[しばしば]:often/again and again/frequently, 数[かず]:number/amount, 存在[そんざい]:existence/being, きっと:surely/undoubtedly|sternly
見える世界は 人の数だけ
存在しているんですよ きっと｡
Well, I believe there are as many
perspectives as there are people.
水平線[すいへいせん]:horizon (related to sea or lakes)
私が見ている水平線よりも
For example, you can see a horizon
farther out than the one I can see.
水平線[すいへいせん]:horizon (related to sea or lakes), 遠い[とおい]:far/distant
咲太くんが見ている
水平線のほうが遠いように｡
海風[かいふう, うみかぜ]:sea breeze
この海風も そうです｡
The same goes for this sea breeze.
気持ち[きもち]:feeling|preparedness|thanks|
気持ちいいって思う人もいれば
Some find it pleasant,
肌[はだ, はだえ]:skin|body (in the context of intimate bodily contact)|surface|, 髪[かみ]:hair (on the head), べとつく:to be sticky
肌や髪が べとつくから
while others dislike it because
it makes their skin or hair sticky.
好き[すき]:liking/fondness/love, 好き[ずき]:-phil/-phile|being attractive (to)
好きじゃないっていう人も
いるんです｡
Since fate has brought us together like this,
出会う[であう]:to meet (by chance)|to meet (e.g. of rivers, highways, etc.)|to emerge and engage (an enemy), 縁[ゆかり]:related to (some person or place)/affinity/connection, 縁[えん, えにし]:fate|relationship (e.g. between two people)|family ties||
こうして出会えたのも
何かの縁ですから
人生[じんせい]:(human) life (i.e. conception to death), 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, すてき:lovely/dreamy/beautiful, アドバイス:advice, あげる:to raise/to elevate|to do up (one's hair)
人生の先輩から
すてきなｱﾄﾞﾊﾞｲｽをしてあげます｡
let me give you a magical
piece of advice as your elder.
普通[ふつう]:general|normally|local train, すてき:lovely/dreamy/beautiful
普通 自分で すてきって
言います？
Who calls their own advice magical?
My life was in no terms
filled with dreams and hopes.
人生[じんせい]:(human) life (i.e. conception to death), 決して[けっして, けして]:never/by no means/not in the least, 大きな[おおきな]:big/large/great, 夢[ゆめ]:dream, 希望[きぼう]:hope/wish/aspiration
私の人生にも 決して 大きな夢や
希望はありませんでした｡
人生[じんせい]:(human) life (i.e. conception to death), 意味[いみ]:meaning/significance, 見つける[みつける, みっける]:to discover|to locate|to be used to seeing
それでも 私は自分の人生に
意味を見つけられました｡
Still, I was able to find a purpose for myself.
私はね 咲太くん｡
You see, Sakuta-kun,
人生[じんせい]:(human) life (i.e. conception to death), 優しい[やさしい]:tender/kind/gentle
人生って 優しくなるために
あるんだと思っています｡
I believe life is a series of trials
to make you a kinder person.
優しい[やさしい]:tender/kind/gentle
優しくなるため…｡
A kinder person?
I live my life hoping to become
a kinder person with each passing day.
昨日[きのう, さくじつ]:yesterday
昨日の私よりも
今日の私が ちょっとだけ
優しい[やさしい]:tender/kind/gentle, ながら:while/during|while, 生きる[いきる]:to live|to make a living|to be in effect||
優しい人間であればいいなと
思いながら生きています｡
あのさ 翔子さん｡
何ですか？
Hey, Shouko-san.
What is it?
生きる[いきる]:to live|to make a living|to be in effect||
僕も 翔子さんのように
生きてもいいかな…｡
Can I live like you too?
当たり前[あたりまえ]:natural/reasonable|usual
当たり前じゃないですか｡
Of course you can!
理解[りかい]:understanding/comprehension/appreciation, 苦しみ[くるしみ]:pain/anguish/distress
人に理解されない苦しみを知った
咲太くんなら
Now that you've seen pain
that others don't sympathize with,
きっと:surely/undoubtedly|sternly, 優しい[やさしい]:tender/kind/gentle
きっと誰よりも優しくなれます｡
I'm sure you can become
the kindest person of all.
絶対[ぜったい]:absolutely|absolute|absoluteness, 支え[ささえ]:support/stay/prop, 支え[つかえ]:load on one's chest|obstacle/hindrance, あげる:to raise/to elevate|to do up (one's hair)
絶対に誰かの
支えになってあげられます⦆
I know that you can be a pillar
of support for many.
It was a kind of mindset I'd never imagined.
価値観[かちかん]:sense of values/values/value system
僕が知らない価値観だった｡
Kaede
退院[たいいん]:leaving hospital/discharge from hospital, 冊[さつ]:counter for books|volume, 冊[さく]:imperial edict to confer nobility titles (in ancient China), ノート:notebook/copy-book/exercise book, 買う[かう]:to buy|to value|to stir, 帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
退院した その日 僕は
１冊のﾉｰﾄとﾍﾟﾝを買って帰った｡
The day I was discharged,
I bought a pen and notebook on my way home.
昨日[きのう, さくじつ]:yesterday, 先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy
⦅これを？
昨日 先生が言ってたんだ｡
What's this?
The doc had a suggestion yesterday.
何でもいいから その日あったこと
思ったことを
Keep a diary and write down what you see and feel
each day in your own words.
言葉[ことば, けとば]:language|word|speech, 書く[かく]:to write/to compose|to draw
自分の言葉で
書いてみるといいって｡
はい…｡
まずは名前だな｡
Okay.
Start with the name.
わかりました｡
あっ 待った｡
Got it.
Oh, hang on.
Yes?
はい？
名前なんだけどさ…｡
About your name...
Don't worry. I know how to write it.
きちんと:properly/accurately|neatly, 書く[かく]:to write/to compose|to draw
大丈夫ですよ
きちんと書けます｡
It's "Kaede" with the characters
for "flower" and "maple tree," right?
花[はな]:flower|cherry blossom|beauty||, 楓[かえで, かえるで]:maple (tree) (Acer spp.), 楓[ふう, フウ]:Formosan sweetgum (Liquidambar formosana), 木[き]:tree/shrub|wood, 木[もく]:Thursday|wood (first of the five elements)
お花の ｢花｣に
楓の木の ｢楓｣で
ひらがな:hiragana/cursive Japanese syllabary used primarily for native Japanese words (esp. function words, inflections, etc.), かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.)
｢花楓｣ですよね？
ひらがなで ｢かえで｣にしよう｡
Write it phonetically instead.
ひらがな:hiragana/cursive Japanese syllabary used primarily for native Japanese words (esp. function words, inflections, etc.)
ひらがな？
今 ここにいるのは
Phonetically?
The old Kaede isn't here now. You are.
かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.)
今の かえでだから｡
今まで[いままで]:until now/so far/up to the present
今まで ごめんな｡
Sorry about everything.
お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister, かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.)
お兄ちゃんだけです
かえでのことをわかっているのは｡
You're the only one who sees me for who I am!
Azusagawa Kaede
かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.), 頼む[たのむ]:to request|to call|to entrust to|
かえでのこと 頼むぞ｡
Azusagawa Kaede
Take good care of Kaede, okay?
You take care of Mom too.
父さん[とうさん]:father/dad/papa, 母さん[かあさん, かかさん]:mother|wife (used when speaking to or about one's own wife)
父さんも 母さんのこと…｡
ああ｡
Yeah.
かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.), ゆっくり:slowly/at ease/restful
かえで ゆっくりでいいんだぞ｡
Kaede.
Take your time, okay?
無理[むり]:unreasonable|impossible|forcible||, 父さん[とうさん]:father/dad/papa, 母さん[かあさん, かかさん]:mother|wife (used when speaking to or about one's own wife)
無理はしなくていい｡
父さんも 母さんも
No need to push yourself.
Your mother and I will always be waiting for you.
待ってるから｡
I'm scared of the way everyone looks at me.
怖い[こわい]:scary/frightening|(I'm) afraid
かえでは
みんなの目が怖いです｡
みんな 花楓さんを
見てるんです⦆
They all see Kaede-san, not me.
もちろん:of course/certainly/naturally, 記憶[きおく]:memory/recollection|storage, 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
もちろん僕だって
花楓の記憶が戻ってほしい｡
Of course, I want Kaede to regain her memories too.
戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
花楓に戻ってきてほしい｡
I want the old Kaede to come back too.
場合[ばあい]:case/situation
でも その場合 今のかえでは
どうなるんだろう…｡
But if she does, what happens
to the Kaede here right now?
かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.), 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc., 全部[ぜんぶ]:all/entire/whole
これが かえでの話の全部です｡
That's the whole story on Kaede.
今まで[いままで]:until now/so far/up to the present, 黙る[だまる]:to be silent
今まで黙ってて ごめん｡
いいわよ｡
Sorry I kept it from you until now.
It's fine. You did it for her, right?
かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.)
かえでちゃんのためでしょ？
そうなんですけどね｡
Yeah, but as I watched her
gradually grow closer to you all,
少し[すこし]:small quantity|little while|short distance, 仲[なか]:relation/relationship, 仲[すあい, すわい]:broker/brokerage/brokerage fee
なんか みんなと
少しずつ仲よくなっていく
かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.), 出す[だす]:to take out|to put out|to submit (e.g. thesis)||
かえでを見てると
言い出せなかったんです｡
I couldn't bring it up.
気がする[きがする]:to have a certain mood or feeling/to have a hunch
このままでいいって気がして｡
わかってる｡
I started feeling things were fine
the way they were.
I know. I'm not mad or anything.
怒る[おこる, いかる]:to get angry|to tell someone off|to be angular
別に怒ってないから｡
But...
少し[すこし]:small quantity|little while|short distance, 早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|
でも… もう少し早く
言ってほしかった｡
I do wish you'd told me sooner.
Hey, you are mad!
怒る[おこる, いかる]:to get angry|to tell someone off|to be angular
怒ってるじゃないですか｡
November 17th
おはよう:good morning, かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.)
おはよう かえで｡
Morning, Kaede.
G-Good morning, Onii-chan!
おはようございます:good morning, お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister
おはようございます お兄ちゃん｡
I might be done for!
しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
かえでは もうﾀﾞﾒかもしれません｡
全身[ぜんしん]:whole (body)/full-length (e.g. portrait)|systemic, 痛い[いたい]:painful/sore|exceeding
全身が痛いんです｡
My whole body hurts!
昨日[きのう, さくじつ]:yesterday, いっぱい:one defeat, いっぱい:amount necessary to fill a container (e.g. cupful, spoonful, etc.)/drink (usu. alcoholic)|full, 遊ぶ[あそぶ, あすぶ]:to play|to mess about (with alcohol, gambling, philandery, etc.)|to be idle||, 遊ぶ[すさぶ]:to grow wild/to rage|to do something one enjoys, 筋肉痛[きんにくつう]:muscular pain/myalgia
昨日いっぱい遊んだから
筋肉痛だろ｡
Your muscles are probably sore from yesterday.
熱[ねつ]:heat|fever|zeal|
熱はないな｡
No fever, at least.
金沢ﾛｹ!?
A shoot in Kanazawa?
麻衣[あさごろも, まい]:linen robe, 会[え]:gathering (esp. Buddhist, festive, etc.), 会[かい]:meeting/assembly|association
また麻衣さんに会えなくなるのか｡
I'm not going to see you for a while again?
あさって:day after tomorrow, 都内[とない]:metropolitan area, スタジオ:studio, 撮影[さつえい]:photography (still or motion)/photographing/filming
あさってまでは 都内のｽﾀｼﾞｵで
撮影だから
We're still shooting in a local studio
for the next couple of days,
家[いえ]:house|family|lineage, 家[うち, ち]:house/home (one's own)|(one's) family, 帰ってくる[かえってくる]:to return/to come back
家には帰ってくるわよ｡
so I'll be home until then.
Call me if you need anything.
連絡[れんらく]:to contact|contacting|connection|, 電話[でんわ]:telephone call/phone call|telephone (device)
何かあったら 連絡して｡
何もなくても電話します！
I'll call you even if I don't need anything!
かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.), 意味[いみ]:meaning/significance
今のは かえでちゃんにって意味｡
I meant if you needed help with Kaede-chan.
ただいま:Here I am/I'm home!|presently
ただいま｡
I'm back!
かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.), ただいま:Here I am/I'm home!|presently
かえで ただいま…｡
Kaede? I'm back.
おっ おわ！
何してんだ？
What are you doing?
Owwie...
おとなしい:obedient/docile/quiet, 寝る[ねる]:to lie down|to go to bed|to sleep (lying down)||
ｲﾀﾀﾀ…｡
おとなしく寝てろって｡
I told you to stay in bed.
But I was able to go to the beach yesterday.
昨日[きのう, さくじつ]:yesterday, せっかく:stone burial chamber, せっかく:with trouble/at great pains|rare, 海[うみ, み]:sea/ocean/waters, 行[ぎょう]:line (i.e. of text)|carya (austerities)|samskara (formations)|, 行[こう]:going|type of classical Chinese verse (usu. an epic)|district (of similar merchants)|
昨日は
せっかく海まで行けたので
I don't want muscle soreness
to kill my momentum now.
流れ[ながれ]:stream/current|course of events, 筋肉痛[きんにくつう]:muscular pain/myalgia, 邪魔[じゃま]:hindrance|to visit (somebody's home)|demon who hinders Buddhist training
かえでは このいい流れを
筋肉痛に邪魔されたくないんです｡
外[そと, と]:outside|open air|other place, 外[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|
かえでは 今日も
外に出たいと思います｡
I want to go outside again today!
ﾏｼﾞか｡
ﾏｼﾞです｡
For real?
For real!
And you're debuting your uniform?
しかも:moreover/furthermore|nevertheless, 制服[せいふく]:uniform, デビュー:debut
しかも 制服ﾃﾞﾋﾞｭｰか｡
制服ﾃﾞﾋﾞｭｰです｡
I'm debuting my uniform!
プリン:(custard) pudding, 買う[かう]:to buy|to value|to stir
ﾌﾟﾘﾝ買ってきたぞ｡
わ～い！
I got you pudding.
Yay!
話をそらす[はなしをそらす]:to change the subject (e.g. away from something awkward or inconvenient), くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
ｲﾃﾃﾃ…
話をそらさないでください｡
Owwie...
D-Don't change the topic!
You're fine. The outside world
isn't going anywhere.
焦る[あせる]:to be in a hurry/to be impatient/to be flustered, 外[そと, と]:outside|open air|other place, 外[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, 逃げる[にげる]:to escape/to run away
大丈夫だよ 焦らなくても
外は逃げないって｡
かえでは 大丈夫ですか？
Am I fine?
You are fine.
昨日[きのう, さくじつ]:yesterday, 海[うみ, み]:sea/ocean/waters, 女の子[おんなのこ, おんなのコ]:girl/daughter|young woman, 女の子[めのこ]:woman/girl
大丈夫だ｡
でも 昨日 海で会った女の子を
But I didn't know the girl
we met at the beach yesterday.
かえでは知りません｡
She was Kaede-san's friend, wasn't she?
知り合い[しりあい]:acquaintance
花楓さんの
知り合いなんですよね？
かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.), どういう:somehow/how/in what way, 教える[おしえる]:to teach|to tell|to preach
かえでが知りたければ
どういう子か教える｡
If you wanna know, I'll tell you who she is.
苦手[にがて]:poor (at)/weak (in)|dislike (of)
かえでは 花楓さんが知ってる人が
苦手です｡
I don't like knowing about
people who know Kaede-san.
苦手[にがて]:poor (at)/weak (in)|dislike (of), 怖い[こわい]:scary/frightening|(I'm) afraid
苦手ですけど…
知らないのも怖いです｡
But not knowing about them
scares me as well.
あの子は 鹿野琴美さん｡
She's Kano Kotomi. We've known her
since before kindergarten.
幼稚園[ようちえん]:kindergarten, 通う[かよう]:to go to and from (a place)|to go to (school, work, etc.)|to circulate (e.g. blood, electricity)|, 知り合い[しりあい]:acquaintance
幼稚園に通う前からの知り合い｡
同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway, マンション:condominium (often mid-rise or high-rise concrete)/apartment building/apartment house, 階[かい]:storey|stairs|stage (in chronostratigraphy)|, 階[しな]:article|quality|flirtatiousness, 住む[すむ]:to live (of humans)/to reside/to inhabit
前は同じﾏﾝｼｮﾝの上の階に
住んでたんだ｡
She lives on the floor above our old apartment.
ちっちゃい:tiny/little/wee, 頃[ころ, ごろ]:(approximate) time|suitable time (or condition)|time of year, 頃[けい]:qing (Chinese unit of land area equal to 100 mu), 一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same, 遊ぶ[あそぶ, あすぶ]:to play|to mess about (with alcohol, gambling, philandery, etc.)|to be idle||, 遊ぶ[すさぶ]:to grow wild/to rage|to do something one enjoys
花楓とは ちっちゃい頃から
よく一緒に遊んでた｡
She and Kaede had hung out a lot
ever since they were little.
昨日[きのう, さくじつ]:yesterday, 読み返す[よみかえす]:to reread/to read again, 海[うみ, み]:sea/ocean/waters, らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish
昨日は これを読み返そうと思って
海に来たらしい｡
Apparently, she came to the beach
to read this book again.
The Prince
and His
Poisoned Apple
The Prince
and His
Poisoned Apple
The Prince
and His
Poisoned Apple
The Prince
and His
Poisoned Apple
The Prince
and His
Poisoned Apple
The Prince
and His
Poisoned Apple
The Prince
and His
Poisoned Apple
The Prince
and His
Poisoned Apple
借りる[かりる]:to borrow/to have a loan|to rent, 本[もと]:origin|base|cause||, 本[ほん]:book|this|main||
花楓に借りてた本だそうだ｡
She said she borrowed it from Kaede.
What is this?
何でしょう？
見てもいいですか？
May I look?
Yeah.
I want to be friends
with Kaede-chan again
Kotomi
I want to be friends
with Kaede-chan again
Kotomi
I want to be friends
with Kaede-chan again
Kotomi
I want to be friends
with Kaede-chan again
Kotomi
I want to be friends
with Kaede-chan again
Kotomi
I want to be friends
with Kaede-chan again
Kotomi
friends
こみちゃん…｡
Komi-chan?
Kaede, did you just...
かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.)
かえで 今…｡
Kaede? Kaede!
かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.)
かえで かえで！
The Prince
and His
Poisoned Apple
The Prince
and His
Poisoned Apple
The Prince
and His
Poisoned Apple
The Prince
and His
Poisoned Apple
The Prince
and His
Poisoned Apple
The Prince
and His
Poisoned Apple
The Prince
and His
Poisoned Apple
The Prince
and His
Poisoned Apple
The Prince
and His
Poisoned Apple
The Prince
and His
Poisoned Apple
Teenage Pig Doesn't
Dream of Bunny Girls
Frankly speaking,
Fujisawa General Hospital
正直[しょうじき]:honesty/integrity|honestly, かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.), 意識[いしき]:consciousness|awareness|mano-vijnana (mental consciousness, cognizer of sensory information), 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
正直なところ
かえでさんの意識が戻るまで
it's hard for me to say anything
until she regains consciousness.
はっきり:clearly/plainly|to be clear, 言える[いえる]:to be possible to say/to be able to say
はっきりしたことは言えません｡
目が覚める[めがさめる]:to awaken/to perk up/to snap out (of something)
ですが 目が覚めたときには
However, when she does wake up,
記憶[きおく]:memory/recollection|storage, 変化[へんか]:change|variety|inflection|, 変化[へんげ]:shapeshifting (of an animal or spirit)|incarnation|transformation, 生じる[しょうじる]:to produce/to yield|to result from, 可能性[かのうせい]:potentiality/likelihood/possibility
記憶に何らかの変化が
生じる可能性があります｡
there's a chance her memories
will have changed in some way.
それは どういう？
What do you mean by that?
Miss Azusagawa Kaede
姫[ひめ]:young lady of noble birth|girl|small|, 様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state, 柄[え]:handle/grip|stalk (of a mushroom, leaf, etc.), 柄[がら]:pattern|body build|essential qualities|
まっ かえでは お姫様って
柄でもないけどな｡
Well, Kaede isn't much of a princess.
かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.)
ん…｡
かえで？
Kaede?
お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister
お兄ちゃん… ここは？
Onii-chan?
Where am I?
倒れる[たおれる]:to fall|to be forced to bed (by illness, etc.)|to die||, 救急車[きゅうきゅうしゃ]:ambulance, 運ぶ[はこぶ]:to carry|to come|to wield (a tool, etc.)|
倒れて 救急車で
運ばれたんだよ｡
You collapsed and were
brought here by ambulance.
お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister, かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.), 着替える[きがえる, きかえる]:to change one's clothes, させる:to make (someone) do|to allow (someone) to, させる:(usu. followed by a negative form) worth special consideration
お兄ちゃんが かえでを
着替えさせたんですか？
Did you change my clothes?
安心[あんしん]:relief/peace of mind, 安心[あんじん]:obtaining peace of mind through faith or ascetic practice, 看護師[かんごし]:(hospital) nurse/registered nurse/RN, 麻衣[あさごろも, まい]:linen robe
違うから安心しろ｡
看護師さんと麻衣さん
Relax. It wasn't me.
It was the nurse and Mai-san.
Toyohama helped, too.
手伝う[てつだう]:to help/to assist|to contribute to, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
豊浜にも手伝ってもらった｡
I wouldn't have minded if you had.
お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister
そこはお兄ちゃんでもいいんです｡
かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.)
かえで… なんだよな？
かえでは かえでですよ？
You are Kaede... right?
Yes, I am.
November 18th
かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.), 意識[いしき]:consciousness|awareness|mano-vijnana (mental consciousness, cognizer of sensory information), 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
[℡]かえでの意識が戻りました｡
Kaede came to.
検査[けんさ]:inspection (e.g. customs, factory)/examination/scan (e.g. MRI, PET, etc.), 結果[けっか]:result/consequence|coming to fruition, 異常[いじょう]:strangeness/abnormality/disorder
[℡]検査結果も異常はないようで
The tests didn't show anything abnormal,
so she may be discharged today.
退院[たいいん]:leaving hospital/discharge from hospital, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
今日にも退院できるみたいです｡
よかった｡
Thank goodness.
今回[こんかい]:now/this time/lately, 倒れる[たおれる]:to fall|to be forced to bed (by illness, etc.)|to die||
ただ 今回倒れたのは
But...
Her collapsing might be a sign of
Kaede's memories returning, it seems.
かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.), 記憶[きおく]:memory/recollection|storage, 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from, 兆候[ちょうこう]:sign/indication/omen, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
かえでの記憶が
戻る兆候かもしれないそうです｡
昔[むかし]:olden days/former, かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.), 記憶[きおく]:memory/recollection|storage, 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from, 場合[ばあい]:case/situation
もし 昔のかえでの記憶が
戻った場合
If the old Kaede's memories return,
今度[こんど]:this time|next time|recently, かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.), 記憶[きおく]:memory/recollection|storage, 消える[きえる]:to go out/to vanish/to disappear, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.), 可能性[かのうせい]:potentiality/likelihood/possibility
今度は 今のかえでの記憶が
消えてしまう可能性があるって｡
it's possible the current Kaede's memories
could be lost this time.
そんな…｡
What?
Was Dad here?
お父さん[おとうさん, おとっさん]:father/dad/papa
お父さん 来てたんですか？
ああ｡
Yeah. He was worried about you.
かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.), 心配[しんぱい]:worry/concern|care
かえでのこと心配してた｡
かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.), いちばん:number one/first|best
なあ かえで 今いちばん
何がしたい？
Say, Kaede.
What do you wanna do most right now?
プリン:(custard) pudding, 食べる[たべる]:to eat|to live on (e.g. a salary)/to live off, 退院[たいいん]:leaving hospital/discharge from hospital, 祝い[いわい, ゆわい]:congratulation/congratulations/celebration, 的[てき]:-like/typical, 的[まと]:mark/target
ﾌﾟﾘﾝが食べたいです｡
退院祝い的なやつだ｡
I want to eat pudding.
I mean to celebrate your discharge.
もっと:(some) more/even more/longer, 大きな[おおきな]:big/large/great
もっと大きなことでいいんだぞ｡
You can dream a little bigger, you know?
大きな[おおきな]:big/large/great, プリン:(custard) pudding, 食べる[たべる]:to eat|to live on (e.g. a salary)/to live off
大きなﾌﾟﾘﾝが食べたいです！
まあ それは食べるとして
I want to eat a big pudding!
Let's assume you get your pudding.
例えば[たとえば]:for example/for instance/e.g., パンダ:panda, 見に行く[みにいく]:to go to see (something, someone)/to visit, 感じ[かんじ]:feeling/sense/impression
例えば ﾊﾟﾝﾀﾞを見に行くとか
そういう感じの｡
What else? Wanna go see the pandas
or something like that?
パンダ:panda, 番[ばん]:number (in a series)|(one's) turn|watch|, 番[つがい]:(one) pair (e.g. of birds)/brace|joint
ﾊﾟﾝﾀﾞは２番です｡
１番は？
The pandas are number two.
What's number one?
番[ばん]:number (in a series)|(one's) turn|watch|, 番[つがい]:(one) pair (e.g. of birds)/brace|joint
１番は…｡
Number one is...
I want to go to school.
学校[がっこう]:school
学校に行きたいです｡
November 19th
かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.), 学校[がっこう]:school
かえでが
学校に行きたいって言ってる｡
Kaede's saying she wants to go to school.
願い[ねがい]:desire/wish/request, 叶える[かなえる]:to grant (request, wish)/to answer (prayer)|to fulfill (conditions), あげる:to raise/to elevate|to do up (one's hair)
そうか｡
僕は その願いを叶えてあげたい｡
Really?
I want to make sure she does.
中学校[ちゅうがっこう]:junior high school/middle school/lower secondary school, 明日[あした, あす]:tomorrow|near future, 事情を話す[じじょうをはなす]:to explain the situation
わかった 中学校には
明日のうちに事情を話しておく｡
Got it. I'll talk to her middle school tomorrow.
咲太…｡
ん？
Sakuta...
Are you eating right?
きちんと:properly/accurately|neatly, 食う[くう]:to eat|to live|to bite||, 食べる[たべる]:to eat|to live on (e.g. a salary)/to live off
きちんとﾒｼを食ってるか？
食べてるよ｡
I am.
そうか…｡
ん…｡
Really?
Yeah.
落ち着く[おちつく]:to calm down|to calm down|to settle down (in a location, job, etc.)||
あとな 落ち着いてからで
いいんだが…｡
Also... This can wait until after
things calm down, but...
つきあい:association/socializing/socialising
何？
お前が おつきあいしている
What's up?
Introduce me to the girl you're dating.
紹介[しょうかい]:introduction/presentation/referral, なさる:to do
彼女のことを紹介しなさい｡
えっと:let me see/well/errr ..., 落ち着く[おちつく]:to calm down|to calm down|to settle down (in a location, job, etc.)||
あ… えっと 落ち着いたらで｡
Oh, uh...
After things calm down.
November 20th
The Kanazawa shoot's scheduled
for two weeks, right?
週間[しゅうかん]:weeks (period of), 予定[よてい]:plans/arrangement/schedule
金沢ﾛｹ ２週間の予定でしたっけ？
うん｡
Yeah. I know you'll be lonely without me,
会[え]:gathering (esp. Buddhist, festive, etc.), 会[かい]:meeting/assembly|association, 寂しい[さびしい, さみしい]:lonely/lonesome/solitary
私に会えなくて
寂しいと思うけど
ちゃんと:diligently/seriously|perfectly, 毎晩[まいばん]:every night, 電話[でんわ]:telephone call/phone call|telephone (device), あげる:to raise/to elevate|to do up (one's hair)
ちゃんと毎晩
電話してあげるから｡
but I'll call you every night.
I'll stand by in front of the phone every night!
毎晩[まいばん]:every night, 電話[でんわ]:telephone call/phone call|telephone (device), 待機[たいき]:alert/standby/await an opportunity, してい:servant/janitor/messenger, してい:older sister and younger brother
毎晩 電話の前で待機しています｡
まじめ:diligent/serious/honest, 勉強[べんきょう]:study|diligence|discount, なさる:to do
まじめに勉強でもしてなさい｡
Study or something instead.
怖い[こわい]:scary/frightening|(I'm) afraid
(のどか)咲太はさ 怖くないわけ？
は？
Aren't you scared, Sakuta?
かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.), 考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||, 怖い[こわい]:scary/frightening|(I'm) afraid, 決まる[きまる]:to be decided/to be settled|to look good in (clothes)
かえでちゃんのこと考えると｡
んなもん 怖いに決まってるだろ｡
When you think about Kaede-chan, I mean.
Of course I'm scared.
I'm about to piss my pants even as we speak.
まじめ:diligent/serious/honest
今も ちびりそう｡
まじめに聞いてんの｡
Hey, I'm asking seriously.
妹[いもうと]:younger sister, 妹[いも]:darling (only of a woman)|one's sister|friend, 兄[あに]:elder brother/older brother, 兄[けい]:elder brother|pronoun or suffix used in reference to an older brother figure/Mister, 漏らす[もらす]:to let leak|to wet one's pants|to give utterance|
でも 妹の前で
兄が漏らすわけにはいかないだろ｡
But there are things a guy can't show
in front of his little sister.
小[しょう]:smallness|short month (i.e. having fewer than 31 days)|elementary school||, 小[こ]:small|slightly less than|somewhat|, 大[おお]:big/large, 大[だい]:the large part of|big|approximate size||, 弱音[じゃくおん]:soft sound, 弱音[よわね]:feeble complaint/whine
小も大も 弱音も｡
Be they soiled pants or weakness.
お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister
僕は お兄ちゃんだからな
どうにかできることなら
I'm her Onii-chan, after all.
If there were any way I could help, I'd love to.
なんとかしたいけどな｡
どうにもできないんだよ｡
ごめん…｡
But there's nothing I can do.
Sorry.
あ～ もう 私 ﾊﾞｶだ！
どうにもできないから
Geez, I'm such an idiot!
I should've known that was why
Onee-chan didn't say anything!
お姉ちゃん[おねえちゃん]:familiar form of "older sister"|form of address for young adult female
お姉ちゃん
何も言わなかったのに｡
I'm so sorry!
ホント:truth/reality/actuality
ﾎﾝﾄに ごめん｡
November 22nd
スクール:school, カウンセラー:counselor/counsellor
(友部)ｽｸｰﾙｶｳﾝｾﾗｰの友部です｡
I'm Tomobe, a school counselor.
最初[さいしょ]:beginning/outset/first, 通学[つうがく]:commuting to school/school commute, 路[みち]:road|distance|the way (of proper conduct, etc.)||, 路[じ]:route|distance travelled in a day|(with decade) one's ...., 少し[すこし]:small quantity|little while|short distance
最初は 通学路を少しだけ
You can start with walking down
the road to school a little.
歩く[あるく]:to walk
歩いてみるところからでも
いいんです｡
学校[がっこう]:school, いきなり:abruptly/suddenly/all of a sudden, 教室[きょうしつ]:classroom|department|single-room school, 保健室[ほけんしつ]:school infirmary
学校も いきなり教室じゃなくて
保健室からでも｡
And once you get to school, you can go
to the infirmary instead of straight to class.
保健室[ほけんしつ]:school infirmary, 学校[がっこう]:school, 行[ぎょう]:line (i.e. of text)|carya (austerities)|samskara (formations)|, 行[こう]:going|type of classical Chinese verse (usu. an epic)|district (of similar merchants)|, ことになる:it has been decided (so) that/it has been arranged (so) that|it is the result (of)
ほ 保健室でも
学校に行けたことになりますか？
D-Does going to the infirmary
count as going to school?
もちろん:of course/certainly/naturally
ええ それはもちろん｡
Of course it does.
But that's not how it works
for everyone else.
でも みんなとは違いますよ｡
そうですね｡
I suppose.
同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway, 見える[みえる]:to be seen|to look|to come, 見える[まみえる]:to have an audience|to face (an enemy)|to serve (esp. as one's wife), 実[じつ, じち]:truth|sincerity|content|, 実[み]:fruit|seed|(in broth) pieces of meat, vegetable, etc.|
だけど同じように見えて 実は
みんな違っているんですよ｡
But everyone's actually different
in their own way, you know?
例えば[たとえば]:for example/for instance/e.g., 背[せい]:height/stature, 背[せ]:back|reverse|height|, 高い[たかい]:high/tall|expensive, 低い[ひくい]:low (rank, degree, value, content, quality, etc.)|low (position)|short (height)|
例えば 背の高い子や
低い子もいますよね｡
For instance, people can be tall,
short, or average, right?
走る[はしる]:to run|to travel (movement of vehicles)|to hurry to||, 得意[とくい]:triumph|pride|one's strong point|, 苦手[にがて]:poor (at)/weak (in)|dislike (of)
走るのが得意な子もいれば
苦手な子もいます｡
They can be fast runners or slow.
それぞれ:each/respectively, ペース:pace
人には それぞれの
ﾍﾟｰｽがあるんです｡
Everyone has their own pace
that's right for them.
かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.), 一生懸命[いっしょうけんめい]:very hard/with utmost effort/with all one's might, 結果[けっか]:result/consequence|coming to fruition
だから かえでさんが
一生懸命やった結果なら
So as long as you give it your all,
学校[がっこう]:school, 行[ぎょう]:line (i.e. of text)|carya (austerities)|samskara (formations)|, 行[こう]:going|type of classical Chinese verse (usu. an epic)|district (of similar merchants)|
それが学校に行けたということで
いいんです｡
it will count as going to school.
Th-Then, do you think I can mark it as complete
just by going to the infirmary?
保健室[ほけんしつ]:school infirmary, 丸[まる]:circle|entirety|money||, 丸[がん]:fishball/meatball|pill
じゃ じゃあ 保健室でも
丸をつけていいと思いますか？
丸[まる]:circle|entirety|money||, 丸[がん]:fishball/meatball|pill
丸？
これです｡
Complete?
Answer
a
call
from
someone
other
than
Onii-chan
Answer
a
call
from
someone
other
than
Onii-chan
Go
see
the
pandas
with
Onii-chan
Go
see
the
pandas
with
Onii-chan
Go
to
school
Go
to
school
Answer
a
call
from
someone
other
than
Onii-chan
Answer
a
call
from
someone
other
than
Onii-chan
Go
see
the
pandas
with
Onii-chan
Go
see
the
pandas
with
Onii-chan
Go
to
school
Go
to
school
Answer
a
call
from
someone
other
than
Onii-chan
Answer
a
call
from
someone
other
than
Onii-chan
Go
see
the
pandas
with
Onii-chan
Go
see
the
pandas
with
Onii-chan
Go
to
school
Go
to
school
Answer
a
call
from
someone
other
than
Onii-chan
Answer
a
call
from
someone
other
than
Onii-chan
Go
see
the
pandas
with
Onii-chan
Go
see
the
pandas
with
Onii-chan
Go
to
school
Go
to
school
Answer
a
call
from
someone
other
than
Onii-chan
Answer
a
call
from
someone
other
than
Onii-chan
Go
see
the
pandas
with
Onii-chan
Go
see
the
pandas
with
Onii-chan
Go
to
school
Go
to
school
Answer
a
call
from
someone
other
than
Onii-chan
Answer
a
call
from
someone
other
than
Onii-chan
Go
see
the
pandas
with
Onii-chan
Go
see
the
pandas
with
Onii-chan
Go
to
school
Go
to
school
Answer
a
call
from
someone
other
than
Onii-chan
Answer
a
call
from
someone
other
than
Onii-chan
Go
see
the
pandas
with
Onii-chan
Go
see
the
pandas
with
Onii-chan
Go
to
school
Go
to
school
Answer
a
call
from
someone
other
than
Onii-chan
Answer
a
call
from
someone
other
than
Onii-chan
Go
see
the
pandas
with
Onii-chan
Go
see
the
pandas
with
Onii-chan
Go
to
school
Go
to
school
Answer
a
call
from
someone
other
than
Onii-chan
Answer
a
call
from
someone
other
than
Onii-chan
Go
see
the
pandas
with
Onii-chan
Go
see
the
pandas
with
Onii-chan
Go
to
school
Go
to
school
Answer
a
call
from
someone
other
than
Onii-chan
Answer
a
call
from
someone
other
than
Onii-chan
Go
see
the
pandas
with
Onii-chan
Go
see
the
pandas
with
Onii-chan
Go
to
school
Go
to
school
O-On this.
Answer
a
call
from
someone
other
than
Onii-chan
Answer
a
call
from
someone
other
than
Onii-chan
Go
see
the
pandas
with
Onii-chan
Go
see
the
pandas
with
Onii-chan
Go
to
school
Go
to
school
Answer
a
call
from
someone
other
than
Onii-chan
Answer
a
call
from
someone
other
than
Onii-chan
Go
see
the
pandas
with
Onii-chan
Go
see
the
pandas
with
Onii-chan
Go
to
school
Go
to
school
Answer
a
call
from
someone
other
than
Onii-chan
Answer
a
call
from
someone
other
than
Onii-chan
Go
see
the
pandas
with
Onii-chan
Go
see
the
pandas
with
Onii-chan
Go
to
school
Go
to
school
Answer
a
call
from
someone
other
than
Onii-chan
Answer
a
call
from
someone
other
than
Onii-chan
Go
see
the
pandas
with
Onii-chan
Go
see
the
pandas
with
Onii-chan
Go
to
school
Go
to
school
Answer
a
call
from
someone
other
than
Onii-chan
Answer
a
call
from
someone
other
than
Onii-chan
Go
see
the
pandas
with
Onii-chan
Go
see
the
pandas
with
Onii-chan
Go
to
school
Go
to
school
Answer
a
call
from
someone
other
than
Onii-chan
Answer
a
call
from
someone
other
than
Onii-chan
Go
see
the
pandas
with
Onii-chan
Go
see
the
pandas
with
Onii-chan
Go
to
school
Go
to
school
Answer
a
call
from
someone
other
than
Onii-chan
Answer
a
call
from
someone
other
than
Onii-chan
Go
see
the
pandas
with
Onii-chan
Go
see
the
pandas
with
Onii-chan
Go
to
school
Go
to
school
Answer
a
call
from
someone
other
than
Onii-chan
Answer
a
call
from
someone
other
than
Onii-chan
Go
see
the
pandas
with
Onii-chan
Go
see
the
pandas
with
Onii-chan
Go
to
school
Go
to
school
Answer
a
call
from
someone
other
than
Onii-chan
Answer
a
call
from
someone
other
than
Onii-chan
Go
see
the
pandas
with
Onii-chan
Go
see
the
pandas
with
Onii-chan
Go
to
school
Go
to
school
Answer
a
call
from
someone
other
than
Onii-chan
Answer
a
call
from
someone
other
than
Onii-chan
Go
see
the
pandas
with
Onii-chan
Go
see
the
pandas
with
Onii-chan
Go
to
school
Go
to
school
Answer
a
call
from
someone
other
than
Onii-chan
Answer
a
call
from
someone
other
than
Onii-chan
Go
see
the
pandas
with
Onii-chan
Go
see
the
pandas
with
Onii-chan
Go
to
school
Go
to
school
Go to school
I think that's fine.
いいと思います｡
I definitely want to go to school, then.
絶対[ぜったい]:absolutely|absolute|absoluteness, 学校[がっこう]:school
で では かえでは 絶対に
学校へ行きたいと思います｡
November 23rd
You're kidding!
ホント:truth/reality/actuality
ｳｿ！
ﾎﾝﾄだって！
It's true!
なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
そしたら あの子
なんて言ったと思う？
What do you think she said then?
かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.), 笑う[わらう]:to laugh|to smile|to sneer|
別に かえでのことを
笑ってるわけじゃないって｡
They're not laughing at you or anything.
Really?
簡単[かんたん]:simple/easy|brief
本当ですか？
そんな簡単に
If you think it's that easy to make people laugh,
you've got another thing coming.
笑い[わらい]:laugh|smile|sneer|, とれる:to come off/to be removed|(of pain, a fever, etc.) to disappear, とれる:to be photographed|to be able to photograph, 大[おお]:big/large, 大[だい]:the large part of|big|approximate size||, 間違い[まちがい]:mistake|accident|improper conduct (e.g. between man and woman)
笑いをとれると思ったら
大間違いだ｡
Th-The road to comedy is an arduous one, huh?
笑い[わらい]:laugh|smile|sneer|, 道[みち]:road|distance|the way (of proper conduct, etc.)||, 道[どう]:road|way|Buddhist teachings||, 険しい[けわしい]:precipitous/rugged|grim
わ 笑いの道は険しいんですね｡
十分[じっぷん, じゅっぷん]:10 minutes, 十分[じゅうぶん]:plenty|division into ten|perfectly, 頑張る[がんばる]:to persevere|to insist that|to remain in a place, 帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home, プリン:(custard) pudding, 食べる[たべる]:to eat|to live on (e.g. a salary)/to live off
今日は 十分頑張ったし
帰ってﾌﾟﾘﾝでも食べるか｡
You've done well for today,
so shall we head back and eat some pudding—
November 26th
学校[がっこう]:school, 覚悟[かくご]:resolution/resignation/readiness
かえでは 今日こそ
学校まで行く覚悟です｡
I'm determined to go all the way to school today.
I'll do my best.
頑張る[がんばる]:to persevere|to insist that|to remain in a place, 焦る[あせる]:to be in a hurry/to be impatient/to be flustered
頑張ります｡
そんなに焦らなくてもいいんだぞ｡
You don't need to rush things, you know?
焦る[あせる]:to be in a hurry/to be impatient/to be flustered
か かえでは焦ってませんよ｡
I-I'm not rushing.
ゆっくり:slowly/at ease/restful
友部さんも
ゆっくりでいいって言ってたろ？
Tomobe-san said you could
take it slow too, remember?
Kaede?
かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.)
かえで？
それじゃﾀﾞﾒなんです…｡
But that won't be enough.
ﾀﾞﾒって？
Enough?
Kaede, let's skip practice today—
かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.), 練習[れんしゅう]:practice/practising, お休み[おやすみ]:holiday|sleep|Good night
かえで 今日は
練習お休みにしような｡
Kaede?!
かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.)
かえで！
Kaede!
かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.), 無理[むり]:unreasonable|impossible|forcible||
かえで 無理しなくて
いいんだって！
You don't have to force yourself!
No, I have to!
しないとﾀﾞﾒなんです！
I don't have the time to take it easy!
かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.), ゆっくり:slowly/at ease/restful
かえでには ゆっくりしてる
時間がないんですよ！
あいつ 知ってたのかよ｡
Damn it... She knew?
What's with that? Too funny.
ウケる:to receive|to catch (e.g. a ball)|to be struck by (wind, waves, sunlight, etc.)||, ヤバい:dangerous|awful|terrific
何それ ｳｹるんだけど ﾔﾊﾞすぎ！
あ？
It's crazy.
Crazy creepy.
うっ… なんで なんで…｡
Why...
Why?
Kaede?
かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.)
かえで…｡
Why can't I do it?
どうしてﾀﾞﾒなんですか！
I want to go to school,
so why am I freezing up?
学校[がっこう]:school
なんで かえでは
学校に行きたいのに
動く[うごく]:to move|to operate|to be touched||
動いてくれないんですか！
Kaede...
かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.), 帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
かえで…｡
かえでは帰りません！
I'm not going home! I'm not!
帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home, 学校[がっこう]:school, 行[ぎょう]:line (i.e. of text)|carya (austerities)|samskara (formations)|, 行[こう]:going|type of classical Chinese verse (usu. an epic)|district (of similar merchants)|
帰りません… 学校に
行けるようになるまで
I'll keep practicing until I make it to school.
練習[れんしゅう]:practice/practising
練習します 練習します…｡
I'll keep practicing!
かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.), 学校[がっこう]:school, 行[ぎょう]:line (i.e. of text)|carya (austerities)|samskara (formations)|, 行[こう]:going|type of classical Chinese verse (usu. an epic)|district (of similar merchants)|, してやる:to do for (someone)
わかった 僕が かえでを
学校に行けるようにしてやる｡
Gotcha.
I'll make sure you get to school.
えっ 本当ですか？
本当だ｡
What? Really?
Really. But we're taking a small break
before resuming practice.
練習[れんしゅう]:practice/practising, 再開[さいかい]:reopening/resumption/restarting, 休憩[きゅうけい]:rest/break/recess
だけど 練習の再開は
ちょっと休憩してからだ｡
休憩[きゅうけい]:rest/break/recess
休憩ですか？
ああ｡
A break?
Yeah. At a very special place.
とっておき:reserve/spare|treasured, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
とっておきの場所でな｡
That's a lot of people.
いっぱい:one defeat, いっぱい:amount necessary to fill a container (e.g. cupful, spoonful, etc.)/drink (usu. alcoholic)|full, 程度[ていど]:degree/amount/grade, ひるむ:to falter/to flinch (from)/to recoil (from)
人がいっぱいいます｡
この程度で ひるんでたら
If you let this shake you,
you'll never go to school.
学校[がっこう]:school, 行[ぎょう]:line (i.e. of text)|carya (austerities)|samskara (formations)|, 行[こう]:going|type of classical Chinese verse (usu. an epic)|district (of similar merchants)|, 頑張る[がんばる]:to persevere|to insist that|to remain in a place
学校には行けないぞ｡
は はい 頑張ります｡
G-Got it. I'll do my best.
O-Onii-chan, how much farther
to the special place?
お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister, とっておき:reserve/spare|treasured, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
お お兄ちゃん とっておきの場所
まだですか？
Chill. We'll be there soon.
心配[しんぱい]:worry/concern|care, 着く[つく]:to arrive at/to reach|to sit on, 着く[はく]:to put on (or wear) lower-body clothing (i.e. pants, skirt, etc.)|to affix a sword to one's hip|to affix a bowstring to a bow
心配するな すぐ着く｡
Are we there yet, Onii-chan?
お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister
お兄ちゃん まだですか？
もうすぐだ｡
Almost.
Here we are.
着く[つく]:to arrive at/to reach|to sit on, 着く[はく]:to put on (or wear) lower-body clothing (i.e. pants, skirt, etc.)|to affix a sword to one's hip|to affix a bowstring to a bow
ほら 着いたぞ｡
The zoo? It's the zoo, Onii-chan!
動物園[どうぶつえん]:zoo/zoological gardens, お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister
動物園 動物園ですよ
お兄ちゃん！
とっておき:reserve/spare|treasured, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
だから とっておきの場所だって
言ったろ｡
I said it was a special place, didn't I?
どうぞ:please/kindly|by all means, ゆっくり:slowly/at ease/restful
どうぞ ごゆっくり｡
Regular Admission
Enjoy yourselves.
It smells like Nasuno
when she needs a wash.
洗う[あらう]:to wash|to inquire into|to purify (one's heart)|, においがする:to smell/to smell of/to have a smell
洗ってない なすのの
においがします｡
獣[けもの, けだもの]:beast/brute/animal, 獣[しし]:beast (esp. one used for its meat, such as a boar or a deer)|hunting (of animals such as boar, deer, etc.), くさい:stinking/smelly|suspicious, くさい:salvation (from suffering based on Buddha's teachings)
するな 獣くさいな｡
It kinda does, huh?
I smell fur in the air.
パンダ:panda, お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister
あっ ﾊﾟﾝﾀﾞ！
お兄ちゃん ﾊﾟﾝﾀﾞですよ！
Pandas?
Onii-chan, pandas!
They have pandas here!
Y-Yeah...
パンダ:panda
ﾊﾟﾝﾀﾞがいるんですよ！
おお…｡
It's a panda!
パンダ:panda, 歩く[あるく]:to walk
ﾊﾟﾝﾀﾞです！ ﾊﾟﾝﾀﾞが歩いてます！
歩いてるな｡
A panda is walking!
Look at it go.
That one over there is eating!
あっち:that way (direction distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|that one (something physically distant from both speaker and listener, or something not visible but known by both speaker and listener), パンダ:panda, 食べる[たべる]:to eat|to live on (e.g. a salary)/to live off
あっちのﾊﾟﾝﾀﾞは食べてます！
食べてるな｡
Look at it eat.
パンダ:panda, 大きい[おおきい]:big/large/great, さすが:as one would expect|still/all the same, さすが:dagger, ジャイアント:giant
ﾊﾟﾝﾀﾞ 大きいです｡
さすがｼﾞｬｲｱﾝﾄだな｡
These pandas are huge!
They're not called giant for nothing.
あっ こっち見ましたよ｡
It looked this way!
パンダ:panda, 食べる[たべる]:to eat|to live on (e.g. a salary)/to live off, 始める[はじめる]:to start|to open (e.g. a store)|to start ...
ﾊﾟﾝﾀﾞ また食べ始めました｡
It started eating again.
Bamboo leaves aren't very nutritious,
笹[ささ]:bamboo grass/generally smaller species of running bamboo that do not shed their sheaths (e.g. Sasa spp.), 栄養[えいよう]:nutrition/nourishment, 大半[たいはん]:majority/more than half|mostly, 食事[しょくじ]:meal|to eat
笹は栄養がないから
１日の大半を食事に使わないと
so pandas have to spend
most of the day eating to survive.
パンダ:panda, 生きる[いきる]:to live|to make a living|to be in effect||, いける:to arrange (flowers)/to plant|living, いける:to be good (at)/to go well|to look (taste, etc.) good, テレビ:television/TV
ﾊﾟﾝﾀﾞは生きていけないんだって
前にﾃﾚﾋﾞでやってたな｡
I saw that in a TV documentary once.
パンダ:panda, 大変[たいへん]:very|immense|serious||, 頑張る[がんばる]:to persevere|to insist that|to remain in a place, 生きる[いきる]:to live|to make a living|to be in effect||
ﾊﾟﾝﾀﾞも大変ですね｡
みんな 頑張って生きてるんだな｡
Pandas have it rough, huh?
We're all trying our best
to make it through life.
お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister, レッサーパンダ:red panda (Ailurus fulgens)/lesser panda
(かえで)お兄ちゃん
ﾚｯｻｰﾊﾟﾝﾀﾞです｡
Onii-chan, it's a lesser panda.
小さい[ちいさい]:small/little/tiny
ﾚｯｻｰだな｡
小さいです｡
Lesser it is.
It's tiny.
Hence the "lesser."
ﾚｯｻｰだしな｡
でも かわいいです｡
But it's very cute.
やっぱり:too/also|still, パンダ:panda, 派[は]:clique/faction/school
かえでは やっぱりﾊﾟﾝﾀﾞ派です｡
I really am a panda fan.
I don't want to say goodbye.
パンダ:panda, 別れ[わかれ]:parting/separation/farewell, 寂しい[さびしい, さみしい]:lonely/lonesome/solitary
ﾊﾟﾝﾀﾞとお別れは寂しいです｡
また来ればいいんだよ｡
You can just come again.
でも かえでは…｡
But I...
年間[ねんかん]:years (period of), パスポート[パスポート]:passport, かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.)
これ 年間ﾊﾟｽﾎﾟｰﾄ かえでの分｡
Yearly Pass
Azusagawa Kaede
Here. A yearly pass.
Yearly Pass
Azusagawa Kaede
It's yours.
あ…｡
これがあれば
With this, you can meet the pandas
every day if you want.
毎日[まいにち]:every day, パンダ:panda, 会[え]:gathering (esp. Buddhist, festive, etc.), 会[かい]:meeting/assembly|association, すごい:terrible/dreadful|amazing (e.g. of strength)
毎日だってﾊﾟﾝﾀﾞに会えるぞ｡
す すごいです！
A-Amazing!
You're the best, Onii-chan!
お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister, やっぱり:too/also|still
お兄ちゃんは やっぱり
お兄ちゃんです！
かえでは またここに来ても
いいんですね？
I can come here again, right?
Obviously.
当たり前[あたりまえ]:natural/reasonable|usual
そんなの当たり前だろ｡
A yearly pass isn't cheap.
せっかく:stone burial chamber, せっかく:with trouble/at great pains|rare, 年間[ねんかん]:years (period of), 買う[かう]:to buy|to value|to stir
せっかく年間ﾊﾟｽ買ったんだし
Gotta use it several times,
or it won't be worth it.
何度[なんど]:how many times?/how often?, もったい:superior airs/air of importance|overemphasis
何度も来ないと
もったいないからな｡
Yearly Pass
Azusagawa Kaede
I want to come here again and again
and get the money's worth.
何度[なんど]:how many times?/how often?, かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.), もとをとる:to recover a cost/to recover an expense/to get a return on one's investment
何度も来て かえでも
もとをとりたいと思います｡
Yeah.
かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.), 買い物[かいもの]:shopping/purchased goods, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
かえでにも買い物ができました｡
持とうか？
I was able to do some shopping too.
Want me to carry it?
かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.), 買う[かう]:to buy|to value|to stir, プリン:(custard) pudding, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
かえでの買ったﾌﾟﾘﾝなので
かえでが持ちます｡
I bought this pudding, so I'll carry it.
お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister, おうち:hollow/low ground/basin, おうち:interior/backwoods/hinterland, あっち:that way (direction distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|that one (something physically distant from both speaker and listener, or something not visible but known by both speaker and listener)
お兄ちゃん おうちは
あっちですよね？
Onii-chan, isn't home that way?
There's a shortcut this way.
近道[ちかみち]:short way/shortcut
こっちに近道があるんだよ｡
I had no idea there was a shortcut.
近道[ちかみち]:short way/shortcut, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
近道なんて 知りませんでした｡
辺り[あたり, ほとり]:on the bank of|(in the) neighbourhood|around (Sunday, last year, etc...)|, 素人[しろうと, しろと]:amateur|respectable woman (not a prostitute, hostess, geisha, etc.)|unlicensed prostitute
かえでは まだ
この辺りの素人だからな｡
Well, you're a newbie when it comes to this area.
And you're an expert?
お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister, 上級者[じょうきゅうしゃ]:advanced student/advanced learner/advanced practitioner, もはや:already/now|no longer
お兄ちゃんは上級者なんですか？
もはやﾌﾟﾛと言っていい｡
You could even call me a pro.
Wow!
すごい:terrible/dreadful|amazing (e.g. of strength)
すごいです｡ ん？
お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister, 学校[がっこう]:school
えっ お兄ちゃん
ここ… 学校ですよ!?
Onii-chan, this is...
I-It's school!
It's late, so keep it down.
夜[よる, よ]:evening/night, 夜[や]:counter for nights, 静か[しずか]:quiet|slow|calm
もう夜だから静かにな｡
お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister
よっと…｡
ﾀﾞ ﾀﾞﾒですよ お兄ちゃん｡
Hup.
Y-You can't, Onii-chan!
ほれ…｡
でも…｡
Come on.
But...
We're just taking a little peek.
覗く[のぞく]:to peek (though a keyhole, gap, etc.)|to look down into (a ravine, etc.)|to peek into (a shop, bookstore, etc.)||
ちょっと覗くだけだって｡
ちょ ちょっとだけですよ…｡
J-Just a peek, okay?
Your first day of school.
かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.), 初[はつ, うい]:first/new, 初[うぶ]:innocent/naive|birth-, 登校[とうこう]:attendance (at school)/going to school
かえでの初登校だな｡
組[くみ]:set (of items)|group (of people)|typesetting
ここ ３年１組だ｡
Oh, Class 3-1.
かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.), 教室[きょうしつ]:classroom|department|single-room school
ここが かえでの教室なんですか？
Is this my class?
お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister
お兄ちゃん…｡
ん？
Onii-chan.
今度[こんど]:this time|next time|recently, 昼[ひる]:noon|daytime|lunch, 学校[がっこう]:school
今度は お昼の学校に
来たいです｡
I want to come to school during the day next time.
夜[よる, よ]:evening/night, 夜[や]:counter for nights, 学校[がっこう]:school, 制覇[せいは]:conquest/domination/mastery, かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.), 余裕[よゆう]:surplus/margin|composure
夜の学校を制覇した かえでなら
余裕だろ｡
Now that you've conquered it at night,
it'll be a piece of cake.
ノート:notebook/copy-book/exercise book, 書く[かく]:to write/to compose|to draw, 目標[めじるし]:mark/sign/landmark, 目標[もくひょう]:mark/objective/target, 全部[ぜんぶ]:all/entire/whole, 丸[まる]:circle|entirety|money||, 丸[がん]:fishball/meatball|pill
今日で ﾉｰﾄに書いた目標の全部に
丸がつけられます｡
After today, I can mark all the goals
in the notebook done.
ああ もうそんなか｡
All of them already?
With pandas, pudding,
and school, it's all complete!
パンダ:panda, プリン:(custard) pudding, 学校[がっこう]:school, コンプリート:complete
ﾊﾟﾝﾀﾞとﾌﾟﾘﾝと学校で ｺﾝﾌﾟﾘｰﾄです｡
お祝い[おいわい]:congratulation/congratulations/celebration
じゃあ お祝いしないとな｡
はい！
We'd better celebrate, then.
Yeah!
学校[がっこう]:school, 三角[さんかく]:triangle/triangular
あ でも 学校は
まだ三角にしておきます｡
Oh, but I'll mark school partially done for now.
丸[まる]:circle|entirety|money||, 丸[がん]:fishball/meatball|pill
丸でもいいんじゃないか？
Why not fully?
I'll do that after I go to school in the day.
昼[ひる]:noon|daytime|lunch, 学校[がっこう]:school
それは
お昼の学校に行ってからです｡
That so?
気がする[きがする]:to have a certain mood or feeling/to have a hunch
そっか…｡
なんだかできる気がしてきました｡
I'm starting to feel like I can do it.
かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.), 明日[あした, あす]:tomorrow|near future, 昼[ひる]:noon|daytime|lunch, 学校[がっこう]:school, 行[ぎょう]:line (i.e. of text)|carya (austerities)|samskara (formations)|, 行[こう]:going|type of classical Chinese verse (usu. an epic)|district (of similar merchants)|, 気がする[きがする]:to have a certain mood or feeling/to have a hunch
かえで 明日は お昼の学校に
行けるような気がします｡
I think I can go to school during the day tomorrow!
明日[あした, あす]:tomorrow|near future, 楽しみ[たのしみ]:enjoyment/pleasure|anticipation
そうだな｡
明日が楽しみです｡
I guess.
I'm so excited about tomorrow!
明日[あした, あす]:tomorrow|near future, 待ち遠しい[まちどおしい, まちどうしい]:looking forward to/anxiously awaited
明日が待ち遠しいです！
I can't wait for tomorrow!
November 27th
かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.), 朝[あさ, あした]:morning, 朝[ちょう]:dynasty|reign|period||, 寝る[ねる]:to lie down|to go to bed|to sleep (lying down)||
かえで 朝だぞ
まだ寝てるのか？
Kaede, it's morning.
You're still asleep?
おはよう:good morning, お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister
おはよう お兄ちゃん｡
Morning, Onii-chan.
Huh? You're Onii-chan, right?
お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister
あれ？ お兄ちゃんだよね？
Yeah.
My legs are so stiff.
足[あし]:foot|leg|gait||, 足[そく]:counter for pairs (of socks, shoes, etc.), パンパン:kapow/bang/slap
あ～ 足がﾊﾟﾝﾊﾟﾝ｡
Well, you did run all around the zoo yesterday.
昨日[きのう, さくじつ]:yesterday, 動物園[どうぶつえん]:zoo/zoological gardens, はしゃぐ:to make merry/to frolic/to be in high spirits
昨日 動物園で はしゃいだからな｡
動物園？
The zoo? No way.
お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister
行ってないよ
お兄ちゃん どうしたの？
What's wrong with you, Onii-chan?
かえで:maple (tree) (Acer spp.)
かえで お前…｡
Kaede, are...
Huh? Was my room always like this?
部屋[へや]:room|apartment|stable
あれ？ 私の部屋こんなだっけ？
お前…｡
ん？
Are...
花楓… なのか？
Are you Kaede?
Who else would I be?
当たり前[あたりまえ]:natural/reasonable|usual, お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister
当たり前だよ
もうお兄ちゃん 何言ってんの？
Whatcha talking about, Onii-chan?
That's my Onii-chan.
A total pig.
Next Episode
#13: The Dawn After an Endless Night